All right. Well, folks, thanks for being
here. Excited to chat more about how to
engineer voice agents, you know, high
quality, low latency at scale. First,
maybe a little bit about me. My name is
Rishab. I work at a company called
Together AI. I lead the voice AI team
there.
Prior to Together, I was the co-founder
CEO of a company called Refuel that was
acquired by Together last year. But
generally been building AI and machine
learning infrastructure for about a
decade.
For folks who maybe don't know about
Together, Together is building the AI
native cloud. What that really means is
for companies that are looking to train
models and need access to reliable
compute, or you want to do inference at
scale, we're probably a very good fit
for you. We work with, you know, there's
a million plus developers. We closely
work with hundreds of companies and, you
know, very proud to be working with
companies like Cursor and Deck again.
Okay, here is the agenda for today. So,
we're going to first talk about, you
know, why we're talking about voice,
although the previous speaker alluded to
a lot of interesting things that he's
doing with voice. But why does voice
really matter? What does it actually
take to build voice agents at scale?
What are the challenges? We'll talk
about this pipeline architecture, which
is becoming the dominant way to build
agents in production today.
We'll go a little bit deep dive a little
bit. We'll look at all the components.
We'll look at the system and trade-offs.
And then finally, we'll chat about maybe
what might be the next generation of
building voice agents in the coming
months and years.
Okay, so starting with why voice
matters. Well,
there's billions of phone calls a year
that are still handled by humans. I am
pretty sure all of us have the
experience of calling customer support,
asking about the status of our order,
looking to change the reservation.
We've also probably had the experience
of calling a doctor's office because we
got to book an appointment for ourself
or a loved one. And pretty much
everybody here probably has had the
experience of being on hold. Now, it
would be amazing for AI agents to be
able to handle some of these calls for
us.
But really one of the more exciting
directions is, frankly, voice is just
this brand new interface to interact
with systems and computers. Look,
humans, we learned how to talk before we
learned how to read, right? So, this
comes very naturally to us. And
obviously, we're seeing this with
ChatGPT's advanced voice mode. And we're
seeing this with folks who are starting
to directly talk to Cursor, talk to
Claude code in order to get their work
done. And this is, frankly, just the
beginning.
And one of the exciting pieces of 2026
is, you know, building these rich,
high-quality conversations. This is not
the domain of science fiction or
research anymore. This is primarily an
engineering problem today.
Now, why is it hard? Well, there's a few
things that you got to solve first.
First, building voice AI and building
voice agents, this has to be real time.
You know, when humans are having a
conversation, we respond to each other's
cues in something like 300 milliseconds.
And so, if you're talking to an AI and
it's taking more than 500 milliseconds
to respond, you'll start to notice. If
it takes a second, if it takes 2
seconds, people will just hang up. So,
you got to get latency down.
The next thing that matters is you want
it to be a reasonably smart call. You
want to get the work, the job done. And
so, for real-world complex workflows,
you know, the instructions are
complicated. There's a lot of ambiguity.
You have to be good at tool calling
because that's the way you give agents
access to the real world. So, you have a
baseline level of intelligence that you
got to meet.
The third piece that you got to solve
for is
the voice has to be natural enough. It
has to sound pleasant enough.
And this means a lot of different
things. It means, you know, can it talk
to you in your own language with the
right accent potentially?
Can it pronounce your name?
Can it deliver the right emotion that is
needed for a particular situation? A lot
of the things fall into that bucket.
And finally, you know, you could switch
together like a nice demo with one
person calling. But what happens when
you're doing 100 calls, 1,000 calls,
10,000 calls concurrently? Reliability
really starts to matter.
And this is an and problem. You have to
solve every single one of them at the
same time, or you're going to be in a
little bit of a trouble.
So,
at least today, the dominant way of
building these voice agents is this
pipeline architecture or this cascading
architecture, which attempts to solve
all of the problems that I outlined
earlier. Now, there's a few boxes that
are going on, but, you know, it
conceptually it's relatively simple to
understand, which is audio chunks from
an end user that are being streamed in,
potentially to an agent orchestrator,
something like a pipe cat or live kit or
something that is homegrown. And then
essentially, this audio is being fed
into a speech-to-text system that
converts it into text. That's being fed
into an LLM that then decides, do I do a
tool call? What is the output? Produces
text that is then fed into a
text-to-speech model, which starts to
produce audio chunks that are then
streamed back to the end user. So,
that's a rough architecture.
Let's maybe look at like each of the
components
one by one, the components that matter
here.
The first is speech to text. You know,
very much like the ears of your agent
here.
The The performance metrics that matter
here, the first is quality, word error
rate. Now, you know, depending on use
case, the numbers might look different,
but state-of-the-art models are
typically in the 6% word error rate on
open benchmarks. What that really means
is the transcript that is produced by
your model, comparing it with the
reference transcript, that 6% of words
have an error in them.
Now, you can imagine why this might
matter, right? Because if you don't get
the transcript right, you don't get
somebody's name right, you don't get the
name of, let's say, a drug right,
essentially, there's no way to fix this.
Your LLM will make the will carry
forward the mistake. The TTS model will
carry forward the mistake. So, you have
to get it right for the important
keywords.
And then the second metric that matters
often, which is latency driven, is time
to complete a transcript. The way to
understand this is when somebody
completes an utterance, they stop
speaking, how many milliseconds does it
take for you to complete the transcript
and have that be ready for the LLM?
And so, as an example, for some of the
models that we run on Together, we we
get sort of consistently P90 of like 100
milliseconds, which is pretty fast.
Aside from just raw performance, there's
a few other capabilities that matter.
Turn detection, very important, still
somewhat unsolved problem, frankly. That
could be a 20-minute talk in itself. But
really, the best way to understand this
is you've got people who are, you know,
they're talking. Maybe they pause for a
second. But do you actually know? Does
that pause mean their turn has ended?
Are they going to continue talking?
Because really, the last thing that you
want here is for you to for the agent to
start, you know, sending audio back and
talking at this person even though their
turn hasn't ended. We don't enjoy this
in human conversations, and we will
certainly not enjoy this in AI
conversations.
Depending on who your customers are,
language matters, and so being able to
do this for a wide variety of language
and getting it right there, it's
important. And the final piece that I'll
mention, this is somewhat new, is
we're also starting to see
architectures, model architectures that
are streaming native. A little sidebar,
we won't spend too much time on this,
but there's an architectural evolution
for speech-to-text models that is in
progress, which is going from batch
models to stream models.
Whisper is the sort of canonical model
came out a few years ago.
Um, it was trained on 30-second audio
clips.
30 seconds is way too much. You can't
wait 30 seconds to start to do
transcription. So, people have had to
build all sorts of complicated logic
around models like Whisper to do
chunking and to pad it with silences and
then it make multiple calls, stitch that
together to produce the final transcript
in in streaming mode. But recently, and
this is a fairly new model from the
Nvidia team,
instead, you have the encoder of the
model have two interesting
characteristics. The first is it's
trained with different amounts of
look-ahead time. So, it only looks at
perhaps 80 milliseconds or maybe up to a
second of audio instead of 30 seconds.
And it's also able to cache these
activations so that as you kind of make
small steps in audio frames, you're
actually only doing the heavy
computation once. So, again, just kind
of stepping out, but, you know, it's an
interesting direction that we're seeing
to be able to handle streaming
conversations for these voice agent use
cases.
Okay, so that's speech to text. Jumping
into the next part of the pipeline,
which is LLMs. You know, very much the
brains of of your agent.
The performance metric that matters here
first and foremost is streaming latency.
And so, you know, TTFT is the metric
here. And a rough kind of,
you know, metric is like it would it's
usually pretty good if you can get to
300 milliseconds of TTFT
because, you know, you want to start
producing tokens, start feeding that
into the TTS model as fast as possible.
That number, 200 to 300 milliseconds,
has implications for what models you can
use. And so, a good size model typically
ends up being in this 8 to 30 billion
range. If you go any bigger, you'll burn
through your latency budgets. If you go
too small, that has implications for the
intelligence of the model and, frankly,
the tool calling that is needed, which
are both pretty critical if you want to
build a voice agent that does meaningful
stuff in the world.
Okay, text to speech. This is very much,
you know, the voice of your agent.
There's a few interesting things on
on sort of performance and capabilities.
Performance again, you know, the trend
continues. What is the time to first
audio, right? As you get a transcript,
how long does it take to produce the
first audio chunk that can start be
start to be streamed back? And aside
from TTFA,
what is the real-time factor look like?
Real-time factor is, and this is
generally the case for most TTS models,
but what it means is how much
how much audio can you produce in
certain number of seconds of processing
time. So, if you can produce 10 seconds
of audio in 5 seconds, your your RDF is
0.5.
And so, you typically want that to be
less than one so that you're not
buffering.
Um quality is one of the hard ones with
TTS because, you know, there are some
objective measures, but frankly nothing
quite beats listening to audio samples
for the models for the voices that you
care about and getting a feel for is
this the right uh experience that you
want your end customers to have.
Some of the other capabilities, you
know, it's you know, naturalness across
a different uh number of different
voices, being able to pronounce things
exactly right, whether it's, you know,
customer names, whether it's product
names, um being able to have some amount
of control over emotions. And so, you
might see TTS models that allow you to
add these digital little tags which
says, you know, this is happy or angry
or sad. And it's the start, but these
models are getting pretty good uh at
emotional control. And of course,
coverage over language continues to
matter.
Okay, so those are the main components,
but just to kind of zoom out a little
bit. You know, this is still All of
these components are part of this larger
architecture which is multiple models at
being being orchestrated. And so, the
there's a few things that we should
always kind of keep in mind which is
first, you know, there's a latency and
cost budget across these models that
we're thinking about.
A rough rubric is the LLM is going to
take up a majority of it followed by TTS
followed by speech to text both from a
latency and a cost perspective. Um
and so, again, just kind of rough rules
to kind of think about. And one piece
that we didn't mention and we'll come
back to this in a second is so far a lot
of the the numbers that we're looking at
is just engine latency. How much time
does it take the model to produce an
output? But actually, when you're
calling models that might be sitting in
different data centers, there's network
latency as well and that starts to have
an impact. But again, we'll come to that
in
um in one more slide.
Auto scaling is also, you know, somewhat
interesting and tricky to get right for
for agent systems. Of course, you want
to be doing auto scaling to scale up as
demand goes up, scale down potentially,
you know, night times or weekends you
want to scale down seamlessly. Scaling
up, you know,
what we've typically seen as people are
much more aggressive about scaling up
because the last thing you want is, you
know, request to be slowed down or
backed up. So, you typically might auto
scale earlier than you might do with
somewhat more asynchronous systems. And
scaling down is also tricky because you
might actually have these stateful
long-lived connections to your models.
And so, you can't just arbitrarily kill
a pod. You might want to wait for
conversations to kind of fully finish.
So, some interesting nuances with auto
scaling.
And finally, you know, it's like, you
know, global deployments are important
because you want your models uh you want
your system to be as close to your end
users to shave off latency as much as
possible. And of course, you know, if
you're building sort of models in Europe
or in places where residency matters,
you want to be making sure that you have
the ability to deploy wherever you uh we
absolutely need.
I know I referenced co-location. Um
but here's one way to kind of understand
this problem. So, the chart on the
left-hand side, this is very much, you
know, a fairly optimized uh sort of
system where you're doing
a pretty good job with your speech to
text and text to speech and LLM models
where the engine latency is in exactly
the right ballpark. You're doing 100 to
200 milliseconds of time to first token
or audio. But you might actually end up
having your models being sufficiently
far away from your agent orchestrator
that it's taking 75 milliseconds of
network latency. 75 milliseconds is
really not that much. Like, you know,
even in I think like, you know, US West
to Europe would certainly be 75
milliseconds, but you know, depending on
networking it can be much higher as
well. And so,
an interesting kind of direction that
we're seeing folks go is how can you
co-locate all your models and
potentially your agent orchestrator to
either be in the same data center or be
very very close to each other. How can
you get them literally in the same
building? Because that drop from 75
milliseconds to five
basically gets you a 30% reduction in
already a fairly optimized voice agent
setup, right? So, some of these things
um especially again with real-time
systems uh it's just pretty important to
have like fairly deep observability and,
you know, every 10 milliseconds matters.
Okay. So, hopefully that's an
interesting picture on sort of this
pipeline architecture.
Um
but that's not the only way people do
it. One of the other kind of directions
that is becoming interesting is a pure
speech to speech model. And so, instead
of having speech to text followed by LLM
followed by text to speech where you're
sort of coordinating and orchestrating
across a number of different models, um
it's just way simpler if you could have
a pure speech to speech model that still
is responsible for function calling, um
still handles all of the complicated
instructions, uh but just a single model
doing it. And of course, you know, for
folks who've played around with OpenAI's
real-time API, they have a single model
behind the scenes. Uh Nvidia recently
launched a model called voice chat,
again, very similar ideas.
The reason why most of these models are
not used in production too much is
because they have they still have
trouble with instruction following and
tool calling. So, you know, the
real-world experience often looks like
you'll try them
um and then you spend a lot of time just
prompt engineering and hoping to kind of
fix issues and, you know, eventually
move to a pipeline architecture. But
as these models get better, which I'm
confident they will, uh
it has some pretty incredible benefits
because suddenly you don't lose anything
about the nuances of speech when that
speech is getting converted into text.
So, the model will natively understand
what was the tone, what was the emotion,
uh was the user hesitant? That that
stuff will still remain with the model
to make the next kind of decision.
And
this type of model also allows for
um sort of more full duplex homi- like
communication which basically means that
the model can start producing audio
while it's still receiving audio. And
this means that, you know, as your as a
customer is talking to this model,
you can back channel. You can say, you
know, I see or aha like similar to what
a human conversation would look like.
And these models become much better at
handling interruptions and bargins,
which again, with a pipeline
architecture you have to do a lot more
complicated engineering work around.
So,
um
hopefully this kind of points in the
direction of like, you know, what might
be coming in the future. But frankly, we
have a lot of engineering work ahead for
all of these kind of voice interfaces
that still have to be built. Um
if you want to learn more about what
Together does, you know, uh here are a
couple of links. We are hiring. We also
have a booth G1 downstairs. Um happy to
chat more and happy to answer questions.
For voice to function calling use cases,
what sort of um
evals do you use? And then, what score
do you need to get on those evals in
order to have something that's good
enough for production?
Um
that's like the classic answer is like
it depends, you you know, but um I think
in terms of evals like, you know,
there's of course like component by
component evals. So, if we're talking
about sort of like the pipeline
architecture
um and assuming that speech to text is
good, text to speech is good, and the
only thing that we're caring about is
sort of function calling or tool calling
evals on the LLM, then it's very similar
to how one might do evals for tool
calling for LLMs broadly, which is, you
know, was the um uh was the tool call
correct? Was the output actually
possible? There's a bunch of those. One
would imagine that, you know, you'd want
the
uh the tool call structure to at least
be very close to 100% uh
um and then the correctness, again, it
depends a little bit on what does the
use case kind of eventually demand.
One of the other things that we're
seeing is especially to get around to
make models better at tool calling and
because we have to stay within that LLM
budget of like, you know, the models
have to be relatively small,
we do see customers fine-tune smaller
LLMs with their kind of use case
specific data so that they can get tool
calling quality to go up while remaining
a model that is relatively small.
Yeah. When you mentioned about
co-location,
so in that what I understand from that
is you're using you're decreasing the
latency in the network latency. Yeah.
Um it's literally because the the
machines are closer to each other. So,
you
>> that mean like if I'm using cloud
providers or
Uh good question. So, for example, um
you know, let's say you're using let's
say you're building a voice agent here
in London, right? You have servers here,
but you're using perhaps OpenAI's models
for the LLM. And now, odds are that
OpenAI's servers might be somewhere in
the US. So, literally the data has the
the network hop has to be from your
server here all the way there and back.
Uh instead, if you had if you're able to
run, let's say, an open source model in
the data center that you're running uh
your voice agent, now it's basically
going to be intra uh sort of uh like uh
the data center rather than going
um let's say over the Atlantic. So,
that's one way to kind of think about
like and just distance literally kind of
like has that big of an impact aside
from
other kind of networking related
concerns.
Thank you.
Yes. Uh one more question. Um
So, we had
uh when trying this voice pipeline
system that we had to introduce some
guard railing. So, like, let's say we
have classifier model between uh which
just checks that
the model's not offering 8% discount
uh which it's not authorized to do.
Um
How does it present to the pipeline and
how you do that without compromising the
latency and the the
experience? Yeah, it's a great question.
So,
you know, the question is like what if
we have other models like God real
models or other classifiers in the mix?
How does this fit into this
architecture?
You're absolutely right. Like this is
the most kind of basic reference
architecture that one might have. But in
many production settings, there's
actually multiple models that might be
in the mix. The God real or the
classifier, we definitely see people
kind of like start to introduce that
right before the main LLM as well
because maybe you want to check is this
something that um
something that goes to an LLM that
handles refunds versus something that
handles order tracking perhaps. And so
you might have a classifier there. God
reals at the end of the LLM generation
before you produce a response, that also
makes sense. And so often this ends up
growing as the
as the sort of like scope of what you're
hoping to achieve grows.
And it puts real pressure on sort of
like latency concerns and so forth. So,
you know, no easy answers except that it
becomes, you know, one more or two more
components to think about. Have very
clear sort of guidelines and SLAs on,
you know, how much budget can you really
kind of associated with them and then
sort of independently scaling them as
needed. But unfortunately, no
no easy answers. Yes, especially because
when you have things like
like the the edge already Yeah. answer
which was an answer which was already
not
what something it should be but the
classifier the God reals were something
Yeah. I should have lied. You can't take
back things that are spoken. You you
might have to do something Hey, sorry. I
shouldn't have said that.
I need to revoke that or something. So,
this is really a problem I see there.
Yeah, I I think that's spot on. Like
catching all of those before the TTS
model gets invoked is is certainly
important. One of the other things
patterns that at least like we've seen
is sort of this thinker talker pattern
where you might have a small LLM that is
handling
all of the conversation. And so as it
gets sort of text from speech to text,
it produces a response and the response
might look like let me think about it or
let me get back to you. And then it
basically issues one big tool one tool
call to a much bigger model that then
has, you know,
much you know, has better instructions,
has all the tools associated, maybe more
God reals. And then it produces a much
cleaner response that you know, the the
model is much more the the architecture
is like, you know, you're much more
comfortable with. And so that gets fed
into the TTS model to produce a
response.
But you know, in some ways this is kind
of the this is the kind of beauty of
like all of these architectures is, you
know, the components are, you know, you
can we'll only add components. And so it
kind of, you know, pushes more on
sort of reliability, having like, you
know, sort of detailed kind of
observability on every single component.
Yes.
Um um
I was I was just um curious about the
upcoming voice voice
conversations coming out.
And I know that this is upcoming but
at the end of the day all of the
surrounding infrastructure that we have
in the
conversational while we have
conversational systems now and all of
yesterday
pipeline approach, how do we like how do
you do evals in the product
and observability? Like is there a need
to transcribe everything?
Yeah, um very good question. So, how
does sort of observability, logging,
evals change? Um
So,
in some ways so some parts of it can
still remain the same. So, sometimes
what you might have is aside from pure
speech to speech, you might actually
have a
a transcription model that is running so
that you can at least seeing the
transcription allowed at the same time
as the audio is being generated. So,
that gives you some amount of
auditability in terms of what audio is
coming in and what audio is being
produced. But yes, you know, some evals
are going to change. There is no
there's no sort of real concept of sort
of text to speech anymore. There's no
concept of pure kind of text to text
here anymore. And so the evals become
much more
full duplex kind of conversation evals
which is like a much longer conversation
and then, you know, evals and metrics uh
that are sort of focused on that entire
conversation. All right. But what I mean
is like
is the nature of those models are like
able to
output the characteristics of the
the conversation in a way that you can
evaluate is it that native to the
pipeline or is that something on top?
Typically a lot of the evals that would
happen on top on top of the base kind of
inference API.
I think I think we're running out of
time but
Okay.
Um thank you everybody for the for for
being here.